Naomi Riddle papers, 1900-1989
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Naomi Riddle papers, 1900-1989
MS 392
Riddle, Naomi
Performing arts programs, photographs, and personal files of Naomi Riddle (1921-1998), daughter of Jewish actor Tenen Holtz, relating to major productions in Jewish theater history and in the motion picture industry in Los Angeles from 1933-1984.
6 linear feet (5 boxes)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Naomi Riddle, née Tenenholtz, was the younger of two daughters born to Alex Tenenholtz and Ethel Fishman on March 8, 1921, in the state of New York. Her parents, both of Jewish descent, emigrated from the western Russian town of Volkovitch to New York around the year 1900. Her father, Alex Elihu Tenenholtz (February 17, 1887 - July 1, 1971), took up acting around 1906 in the Yiddish Theatre on New York city's lower east side. Alex Tenenholtz, whose stage name was Tenen Holtz, quickly rose to fame with his work in New York repertory theatre. In the mid 1920's, Tenen Holtz moved his family to Hollywood after beginning to take minor roles in silent films. His credits include at least 46 motion pictures from 1926 to 1939. A sampling of some of his roles, credited and uncredited, include: Upstage (1926), Bringing Up Father (1928), Hollywood Hoodlum (1934), and Let Freedom Ring (1939).
Alex's work in the theatre gave Naomi an incredible exposure to the stage and to the business which surrounded it. As a result, Naomi cultivated an appreciation for the performing arts which would play a powerful role in her life. She would go not only to see her father's performances, but to dozens of other productions in and around the Los Angeles area. After graduating from Los Angeles Fairfax High School in 1938, Naomi would spend some years working at Douglas Aircraft and then as a fashion model. During her years as a fashion model in the mid 1940's, Naomi met Dan Otto, a Los Angeles Art Center School instructor. They dated seriously for a couple of years.
In 1954 it is reported that Naomi met Nelson Riddle while working on the television show This Is Your Music. He would later hire her as his full-time secretary in or around 1958. During the mid 1960's when Nelson's marriage to Doreen Riddle began to falter, Naomi became a comfort and good friend to Nelson. On April 11, 1970, Naomi married Nelson Riddle in Los Angeles. On October 6, 1985, Nelson passed away from liver and heart problems. Naomi died on 1998 leaving her and her husband's estates to the University of Arizona.
Organization
This collection is organized into seven series.
Series I: Theatrical Stage Programs, 1934-1984
Series II: Motion Picture Programs, 1933-1969
Series III: Ballet Programs, 1947-1979
Series IV: Instrumental Music and Opera Programs, 1939-1987
Series V: Miscellaneous Programs, 1941-1989
Series VI: Photographs, 1900-1948
Series VII: Personal Files, 1935-1982
Scope and Content Note
Performing arts programs, photographs, and personal files of Naomi Riddle (1921-1998), daughter of Jewish actor Tenen Holtz, relating to major productions in Jewish theater history and in the motion picture industry in Los Angeles from 1933-1984. The collection also includes ballet programs, instrumental programs, and opera programs belonging to Naomi Riddle. Materials within each series are arranged chronologically and by type of item.
Access Terms
Riddle, Naomi, 1921-1998 - Archives - Catalogs.
Tenenholtz, Elihu.
Jewish theater - California - Los Angeles.
Motion picture programs - United States.
Theater programs - California - Los Angeles.
Concert programs - California - Los Angeles.
Playbills - California - Los Angeles.
Container List
- Series 1: Theatrical Stage Programs, 1934-1984
  - Subseries 1: Souvenir Programs, 1943-1976
    - Lady in the Dark, June 22, 1943 (2 items); Jane Eyre, October 1943 (2 items); Florentine Gardens Revue, June 1946 (2 items); Paul Draper and Larry Adler, March 26, 1947 (2 items); Oklahoma, May 1948 (4 items); Magdalena, 1948; Medea, October 5, 1948; Man and Superman; April 1949; New Moon, summer 1949. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Don Juan in Hell, October 1952; Dancers of Bali, November 1952; The Doctor's Wives, April 18, 1953 (2 items); A Midsummer Night's Dream, November 21, 1954 (2 items); Tea and Sympathy, July 9, 1955 (2 items); The Teahouse of the August Moon, August 11, 1955 (2 items); My Fair Lady, June 11, 1957. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Grand Kabuki, June 30, 1960 (7 items); Marcel Marceau, January 25, 1961 (3 items); An Evening with Yves Montand, 2 shows December 1961 and January 1962 (7 items); A Man For All Seasons, ca. 1962; More Stately Mansions, August 1, 1963; Marcel Marceau, December 17, 1965 (4 items); Cabaret, September 7, 1968. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Day After the Fair, 1973; Marcel Marceau, March 1975; The Belle of Amherst, December 1976. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2: Playbills, 1934-1984
    - Yoshe Kalb, May 1, 1934; American Chassidim, November 12, 1934; A Room in Red and White, February 3, 1936; The Children's Hour, July 4, 1936; Bury the Dead, July 11, 1936; One More Genius, August 10, 1936; Dead End, October 3, 1936 (2 items); Jaques Bergson, October 31, 1936; The Learned Ladies, December 11, 1936; The Water Carrier, December 26, 1936; King Richard II, February 6, 1937 (3 items); The Way of the World, February 11, 1937; The Forest Rose, March 19, 1937; His Excellency, March 20, 1937; Hay Fever, April 10, 1937; These Few Hours, October 9, 1937; One Way Street, November 6, 1937; Second Talent Scout Revue, November 26, 1937; Dump Heap, November 27, 1937; The Strong Man, December 3, 1937; Pins and Needles, July 1938; Having Wonderful Time, October 1938; Alien Corn, October 1938; Music and drama program under the direction of Alex Tenen Holz, November 20, 1938; Two-a-Day, November 23, 1938; The Taming of the Shrew, December, 1939. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Meet the People, January 1, 1940 (2 items); No Time for Comedy, January 1940; The Man Who Came to Dinner, February 1940 (2 items); Key Largo, May 23, 1940 (2 items); Desire Under the Elms, January 20, 1941; Pygmalion, February 15, 1941 (2 items); There Shall Be No Night, March 6, 1941 (2 items); The Time of Your Life, April 24, 1941 (2 items); New Pins and Needles, May 1941; What Became of Kitty, July 31, 1941; The Vinegar Tree, April 2, 1941 (2 items). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Kiss and Tell, October 2, 1945; Snafu, November 5, 1945; The Amazon, November 20, 1946; Blithe Spirit, November 21, 1945; Night Must Fall, December 12, 1945; Dancing Girl, December 18, 1945; The Goose Hangs High, December 25, 1945; The Happy Family, December 25, 1945; The Passing of the Third Floor Back, January 1, 1946; Chicken Every Sunday, January 9, 1946; Nine Girls, January 22, 1946; Tomorrow the World, February 6, 1946; Not Since Eve, February 12, 1946; Marta of the Lowlands, February 26, 1946; Alison's House, March 5, 1946; YES is for a Very Young Man, March 13, 1946; Pippa Passes, March 26, 1946; Harriet, March 27, 1946; And Let Who Will Be Clever, April 2, 1946; Squaring the Circle, April 9, 1946; When Ladies Meet, April 17, 1946; Hedda Gabler, April 30, 1946; Angels Amongst Us, May 1, 1946; Madam Sand, May 3, 1946; The Taming of the Shrew / So Wonderful in White / Sunday Cost Five Pesos, May 7, 1946; The Avon Flows, May 15, 1946; Love's Old Sweet Song, MAy 29, 1946; The Girl with the Green Eyes / Lover's Lane, ca. July 1946; Truckline Café, October 16, 1946; Home of the Brave, November 27, 1946; The Mermaids Singing, January 8, 1947; Ten Little Indians, January 22, 1947; The Drunkard, 1948; Sonora Sketch, January 14, 1948; Lend an Ear, August 1948; A Streetcar Named Desire, June 1949. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Shylock and His Daughter, May 8, 1950 (2 items); Take Now Thy Son, March 1953; It's Hard to be a Jew, April 1953; Zog Nit Keinmol, May 3, 1953; 3 For Tonight, June 27, 1955 (6 items); The Lark, October 1956; Fallen Angels, June 1, 1957; The Diary of Anne Frank, August 1957; Cornelis Ortis Skinner presents mono-dramas and monologues, November 13, 1957. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Fourposter, February 11, 1960; At the Drop of a Hat, December 13, 1960; Six Characters in Search of an Author, January 22, 1961; Nellie Forspheis, April 22, 1961; The Hostage, April 28, 1961; A Session with Charles Laughton in Person, May 25, 1961; Electra, September 8, 1961; Dame Judith Anderson presents mono-dramas and monologues, November 13, 1961; The Blacks, May 2, 1962; The Chinese Wall, August 1962; The Hollow Crown, April 2, 1964; Ladies of Hanover Tower, November 1964; The Amen Corner, 1964; Hughie, February 22, 1965; Luther, November 9, 1965; The Owl and the Pussycat, November 22, 1965; Bunraku, April 9, 1966; The Salzburg Marionette Theatre, January 21, 1967; III Acts of Love, February 11, 1967; Basil Rathbone monologues, March 17, 1967; This Day is the First Day of the Rest of Your Life, October 1968; Tom Jones, 1969; Coco, 1969; Rembering Mr. Maugham, July 1969. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Sleuth, May 8, 1970; Long Day’s Journey Into Night, December 21, 1971; Good Evening, 1975; Cages, 1975; Kabuki, June 4, 1976; Quartermaine’s Terms, June 30, 1981; The Way of the World, November 13, 1984. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: Handbills, 1938-1955
    - Arms and the Man / Major Barbara, June 27, 1938; Back to Methuselah, July 25, 1938; Run Little Chillun, October 1938; The Blackbird, October 1938; Of Mice and Men, May 20, 1939; Ladies and Gentlemen, August 5, 1939; Oscar Wilde, May 28, 1940; Tonight at 8:30(first series), August 5, 1940; Tonight at 8:30(third series), August 19, 1940 (2 items); Charlot’s Revue, October 13, 1940 (3 items); The Blackguard, June 24, 1941; Nine Mortal Days, July 3, 1941; State of the Union, September 6, 1946; The Women Have Their Way, November 28, 1946; Anna Lucasta, March 12, 1947; Blackouts of 1947, May 13, 1947; Louisiana Purchase, August 2, 1947; The City Slickers, October 11, 1947; Death of a Salesman, August 23, 1950; The Yale Puppeteers and Forman Brown Musical Revue, 1950; Peter Pan, 1950; Biography by S.N. Berman, ca. 1955. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Motion Picture Programs, 1933-1969
  - Subseries 1: Souvenir Programs, 1936-1969
    - A Midsummer Night’s Dream, April 1936; As You Like It, November 5, 1936; Kentucky, December 14, 1938; Going Places, December 21, 1938; Stand Up and Fight, Jan 9, 1939; Wings of the Navy, January 12, 1939 (2 items); Fisherman’s Wharf, January 23, 1939; Idiot’s Delight, January 24, 1939; Gunga Din, January 24, 1939; Made for Each Other, January 31, 1939; Yes, My Darling Daughter, February 3, 1939; Huckleberry Finn, February 13, 1939; The Little Princess, February 17, 1939; Let Freedom Ring, February 21, 1939; Ice Follies of 1939, March 7, 1939 Dark Victory, March 8, 1939; Three Smart Girls Grow Up, March 20, 1939; Sergeant Madden, March 21, 1939; Wuthering Heights, March 24, 1939; Broadway Serenade, March 27, 1939; The Hardys Ride High, April 18, 1939; The Motion Picture Guild presents a Survey of the Film in America 1895-1930, May 14, 1939 (6 items). (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hamlet, 1948; Cyrano de Bergerac, May 9, 1951; Quo Vadis, 1951; Julius Caesar, 1953; The Ten Commandments, October 3, 1957; Gigi, 1958; Lawrence of Arabia, January 2, 1962; Beckett, 1964 (2 items); The Lion in Winter, November 1968 (3 items); The Seagull, 1968; A Tribute to Orson Welles, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Handbills, 1933-1940
    - Dinner at Eight, October 7, 1933; The House of Rothschild, May 26, 1934; Jesse James, January 10, 1939; The Great Man Votes, January 13, 1939; The Three Musketeers, January 16, 1939; Zaza, February 6, 1939; Persons in Hiding, February 9, 1939; Caf頓ociety, February 9, 1939; You Can’t Cheat an Honest Man, February 14, 1939; Midnight, March 9, 1939; Love Affair, March 10, 1939; The Oklahoma Kid, March 15, 1939; The Hound of the Baskervilles, March 22, 1939; The Lady’s From Kentucky, March 30, 1939; Gone With the Wind, May 29, 1940. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Ballet Souvenir Programs, 1947-1979
  - Swan Lake, performed by Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, December 6, 1947; Sleeping Beauty, performed by Sadler’s Wells Ballet, October 19, 1950 (2 items); The Nutcracker (excerpts)/Grand Pas de Deux from “Don Quixote” / Le Beau Danube, performed by Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, December 6, 1951 (2 items); Designs with Strings / Til Eulenspiegel’s Merry Pranks, by the Ballet Theatre, February 27, 1953; Napoli / The Dying Swan / Concerto / Scheherazade, performed by London’s Festival Ballet, December 30, 1954 (3 items); Les Patineurs / Petrouchka, performed by the Royal Ballet, November 13, 1957 (2 items). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sleeping Beauty, performed by the Royal Ballet, June 28, 1963 (2 items); Swan Lake / Sleeping Beauty / Romance, performed by the Bolshoi Ballet, October 24, 1963 (3 items); Royal Ballet, performed by the Royal Ballet, June 23, 1965 (2 items); Romeo and Juliet, performed by the Stuttgart Ballet, ca. 1967; Sleeping Beauty, performed by the Royal Ballet, 1969; Swan Lake / Romeo and Juliet / The Stone Flower, performed by the Bolshoi Ballet, September 1979. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series 4: Instrumental Music and Opera Programs, 1939-1987
  - Subseries 1: Souvenir Programs, 1939-1963
    - Hollywood Symphony Orchestra conducted by Leopold Stokowski, soloists: Nelson Eddy, Rose Bampton, Dalies Frantz, and Bronislaw Gimpel, October 19, 1939; San Francisco Symphony Orchestra conducted Pierre Monteux, March and April 1949 (3 items); The Los Angeles Philharmonic Orchestra conducted by Arthur Rubinstein, March 19, 1963 (4 items). (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Playbills, 1940-1987
    - 37 programs ranging from March 2, 1940 through February 22, 1987. Programs include Carmen Amaya, Sviatoslav Richter, the Dave Brubeck Quartet, Homage To Stravinsky (composer present), and Peggy Lee. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: Hollywood Bowl Programs, 1941-1969
    - 21 programs ranging from April 13, 1941 through August 19, 1969. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Miscellaneous Programs, 1941-1989
  - Ice-Capades of 1941, April 18, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Tournament of Roses, January 1, 1947 (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Holiday on Ice, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ella’s Birthday, tribute dinner for Ella Fitzgerald, April 28, 1989. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series 6: Photographs, 1900-1948
  - Family photograph of Alex, Ethel, Miriam and Naomi Teneholtz. June 1928; Photograph of Alex and Ethel Tenenholtz, ca. 1930; 14 candid photographs of Naomi Riddle, ca. late 1930’s; 2 photographs of Naomi Riddle performing ballet. ca. 1948. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 38 candid photographs of Dan Otto; Dan and Naomi Riddle as a couple; and several unidentified persons. ca. 1944-1946; 2 photographs of an unidentified man fixing a car. ca. 1945; 7 photographs of cast and crew from Tomorrow the World. February 6, 1946. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series 7: Personal Files, 1935-1982
  - Los Angeles Junior High School diploma, June 21, 1935; Fairfax High School diploma, June 24, 1938; Library clipping, October 1938; Newspaper clipping of Dan Otto, April 19, 1945; Magazine clipping of Dan Otto, May 1948; Driver’s license, March 7, 1975; voter registration documents, 1971 and 1976; Meninger certification, 1973; Estate citation (2 items), 1975; Department of Health anti-smoking documents, March 5, 1979; Decedent documents for Ethel Tenenholtz, June 1982; 2 family trees, ca. 1970’s. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Oversize Items
  - 5 stage photographs of Alex Tenenholtz. April 28, 1916 – 1946. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Portrait of Rivka Fishman (?) on canvas, ca. 1900. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Color photograph of Alex Tenenholtz by Viennese photographer A.H. Schein, ca. late 1910’s. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Matte photograph of Ethel Tenenholtz, ca. 1910’s. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Matte photograph of Alex Tenenholtz, ca. 1910’s. (Box 5, Folder 5)